Alright, next section that we want to talk about is the ovary, and the way I've handled ovary in the text is the first section in your text actually deals with non-neoplastic ovary.
The second part of the text dealing with ovary deals with neoplastic ovary, and I'm going to actually do these in two separate sections.
Now remember, before we can even understand the ovary, we've got to understand the normal.
The functional unit of the ovary is called the follicle.
There are multiple follicles within the ovary, but that is the functional unit.
The follicle basically consists of three cells.
It consists of an oocyte, which is the egg, and then surrounding that oocyte are the granulosa cells, and then outside of the granulosa cells are the theca cells.
Alright, and it's important to remember from normal physiology that recall that what hits the theca cells, it's called the luteinizing hormone.
Luteinizing hormone hits the theca cells, which then induces production of androgen by the theca cells.
At the same time, follicle stimulating hormone hits the granulosa cells, which then allows the granulosa cells to take that androgen and to convert it to estrogen, estradiol, and then that estradiol goes and bathes the egg, and that allows for the egg to mature or the oocyte to mature.
I'm going to repeat that again because it's very high yield to understand these basics for what I'm going to talk about as we move forward.
Luteinizing hormone from the pituitary hits the theca cell.
The theca cell then converts, then produces androgen.
Androgen then goes to the granulosa cell.
Under the influence of FSH, the granulosa cell converts the androgen to estradiol.
Estradiol then hits the egg, and when it hits the egg, it allows for the egg to mature.
So this is the normal.
I'm going to show you this histologically.
Here we have the egg.
This represents the granulosa cells, and this represents the fecal cells.
Again, the fecal cells under the influence of LH will produce androgen.
The granulosa cells under the influence of FSH will convert that androgen to estrogen.
So that's the normal.
Now, once you get the bathing of the egg with estrogen, then eventually what's going to happen is that estrogen is going to result in the proliferative phase within the endometrium as well.
So not only is the egg maturing, but the estrogen goes out into the blood.
It hits the endometrium, causing the endometrium to undergo proliferative phase.
Eventually, there will be ovulation of this egg, and once there's ovulation of the egg, we now go into the secretory phase of the endometrial cycle,
and the residual cells, both the granulosa cells, theca cells, this residual area, will begin to produce primarily progesterone.
And remember that progesterone hits the endometrium and prepares the endometrium via the secretory phase for implantation,
which obviously these cells are hoping will occur because they work so hard to produce this beautiful egg.
So after ovulation, the residual follicle now becomes called a corpus luteum.
The corpus luteum primarily secretes progesterone, which is going to prepare the endometrium for the pregnancy.
It is possible when you have a corpus luteum to get bleeding into the corpus luteum, and that would be called a hemorrhagic luteal cyst.
And that's one way by which you can have a, quote-unquote, mass within the ovary,
but it would actually just not really be a mass, but just a problem of bleeding into a corpus luteum.
Here's what the corpus luteum looks like.
I just want to show you how big it becomes.
Basically, this is the ovary, and you can clearly see that this is the corpus luteum here.
First of all, it's got this yellow color to it because it's producing hormones,
and so that's one important thing to bear in mind.
Another important thing to recognize is how big it is.
It's really almost the size of the ovary, and that's because it really is the functional unit of the ovary,
and once it gets going and its egg is selected for ovulation,
then it really takes over the ovary and drives what the ovary does.
So that's the corpus luteum.
Of course, I've told you that you can actually result, you can get bleeding into the corpus luteum,
which would then expand it further and make it look like a mass,
and that's called a hemorrhagic luteal cyst.
Now, the follicles within the ovary, they can degenerate.
There are so many follicles within the ovary, and it's possible that one or two of those follicles can degenerate.
So imagine if this is the ovary, and I've got all these little circular follicles here.
If one degenerates, what happens when they degenerate is they become big and cystic,
so that when you have a degenerated follicle, it becomes big and cystic,
and most women will have one or two or three follicular cysts, i.e. degenerated follicular cysts, within their ovary.
There is a disorder, however, in which patients can have multiple follicular cysts,
and that's called polycystic ovarian disease, and of course, that is due to a hormone imbalance,
and so we need to understand this disorder a little further.
This disorder is characterized by an increased luteinizing hormone.
That's the way to start when you think about this disorder,
and because there's an increased luteinizing hormone, eventually there's going to be a low FSH,
such that the key characteristic in this disease will be that the LH to FSH ratio will be greater than two.
Now, let me take a step back.
This is a very complicated disorder when you're studying this from the perspective of endocrinology.
And there's a lot of people who have their explanations out there about exactly what's going on.
I'm going to give you one.
You can just take it with a grain of salt, but I think it'll help you to remember what's going on
and sort of try to create a paradigm in your mind in a way that you can remember it.
So let's start this way.
Let's remind ourselves that in this disease, the key problem is an increased LH, right?
So here's the egg, here are the granulosa cells, and here are the, sorry, these are the fecal cells, all right?
Now, the increased LH is going to do what?
It's going to hit the fecal cell, and in response to the increased LH, the fecal cells are going to produce androgen.
All right, so there's going to be a high amount of androgen because there's a high amount of LH.
Now, what that androgen will do is it will go into the blood, and when it goes into the blood,
the androgen will create hertstuism within the patient.
What is hertstuism?
It is excess hair in a male distribution.
So the patients may begin to develop heavy facial hair, for example.
Now, at the same time, some of that androgen will actually go into the peripheral adipose tissue,
and in the peripheral adipose tissue, the androgen will be converted to estrone.
Estrone is the estrogen made by adipose tissue.
Remember that you get peripheral conversion of androgen to estrogen,
and that type of estrogen is called estrone.
Now, these patients tend to be obese, so they tend to produce large amounts of estrone as well.
That estrone will go back to the pituitary and will feed back and shut down production of FSH.
If there's decreased production of FSH, these granulosa cells are going to not be able to do their job.
They're not going to be able to convert androgen to estradiol,
which was the job of the granulosa cells, if you'll recall.
And so what's going to happen in these patients is that they're then subsequently going to get
a degeneration of this follicle,
because they're not able to produce the estrogen necessary to be able to maintain the follicle.
So the follicle will degenerate and become cystic.
And that's what results in the polycystic ovarian classic picture,
the follicular degeneration with multiple cysts within the ovary.
So what is the classic presentation?
You have an obese woman, that makes sense given what I've just talked about,
who has infertility because she's not ovulating.
She has oligomenorrhea because she's not going through,
the entire cycle is messed up because the hormone balance is messed up,
and she's got her Stuart's features,
which means that she's got hair in a male distribution pattern.
Now, that's the classic presentation, and it all ties into what I've already explained.
What I'd also like to remind you of is that a subset of these patients have insulin resistance.
So that 10 to 15 years down the line,
a subset of these patients will actually develop type 2 diabetes mellitus,
and that is high-yield association.
And then another high-yield association is that these patients,
because they have high circulating levels of estrone,
will have an increased risk for endometrial carcinoma.
And recall that endometrial carcinoma, the key risk factor, was estrogen.
So the more estrogen that a patient sees across their lifetime,
the more likely they are to develop endometrial carcinoma.
So the high circulating estrone levels,
because the patient's obese and has large amounts of androgen,
and the androgen gets converted to estrone again,
that high circulating levels of estrone will increase the risk for endometrial carcinoma.
And so that's the key disorder that I want to talk about concerning the non-neoplastic ovary.
And that is also going to be useful for our discussion of ovarian tumors,
but you'll see what I mean when we go to the next section.
So we'll stop there, and then we'll continue with ovarian tumors.